In this place, we reported a new type of microalgae that grew only on top of the spiderwebs that covered the cave entrance. Have you ever seen a spiderweb early in the morning? It's covered with dew, so this microalgae learned that in order to carry photosynthesis in the coast of the driest desert on Earth, they could use the spiderwebs. So here they may access the water from the fogs that regularly cover these areas in the morning. In another cave, we found a different type of microalgae. This one is able to use ocean mist as a source of water, and strikingly lives in the very bottom of a cave, so it has adapted to live with less than 0.1 percent of the amount of light that regular plants need.
En este lugar, informamos sobre un nuevo tipo de microalgas que creció sobre las telarañas que cubrían la entrada de la cueva. ¿Alguna vez han visto una telaraña temprano en la mañana? Está cubierta de rocío, así esta microalga aprendió que para llevar fotosíntesis en la costa del desierto más seco de la Tierra, podrían usar las telarañas. Entonces aquí pueden acceder al agua de las nieblas que regularmente cubren estas áreas por la mañana. En otra cueva, encontramos un tipo diferente de microalgas. Este es capaz de usar niebla marina como fuente de agua, y sorprendentemente vive en el fondo de una cueva, por lo que se ha adaptado para vivir con menos del 0,1 % de la cantidad de luz que necesitan las plantas comunes.
These type of findings suggest to me that on Mars, we may find even photosynthetic life inside caves. And by the way, that's me. (Laughter) Now, for almost 15 years this region of Yungay, discovered by NASA, was thought to be the driest place of this desert, but I knew that it was not. How? You already know the answer. Because I was born and raised in this desert. So I remembered that I usually see fogs in Yungay, so after setting sensors in a number of places, where I remember never seeing fogs or clouds, I reported four other sites much drier than Yungay, with this one, María Elena South, being the truly driest place on Earth, as dry as Mars, and amazingly, just a 15-minute ride from the small mining town where I was born.
Este tipo de hallazgos sugieren que en Marte, podemos encontrar incluso la vida fotosintética dentro de las cuevas. Y, por cierto, ese soy yo. (Risas) Durante casi 15 años esta región de Yungay, descubierta por la NASA, se pensó que era el lugar más seco de este desierto, pero yo sabía que no era así. ¿Cómo? Uds. ya saben la respuesta. Porque nací y crecí en este desierto. Así que recordé que generalmente veo niebla en Yungay, entonces, después de configurar los sensores en varios lugares, donde recuerdo nunca haber visto nieblas o nubes, informé de otros cuatro sitios mucho más secos que Yungay, con esta, María Elena Sur, siendo el lugar más seco de la Tierra, tan seco como Marte y, sorprendentemente, a solo 15 minutos de viaje de la pequeña ciudad minera donde nací.
Now, in this search, we were trying to actually find the dry limit for life on Earth, a place so dry that nothing was able to survive in it. But even here, well hidden underground, we found a number of different microorganisms, which suggested to me that similarly dry places, like Mars, may be inhabited. We even have some preliminary evidences that these microorganisms may still be active in the desiccated state, like walking mummies all around us, and that they may be using UV radiation as a source of energy. If confirmed, this would have a huge impact on our definition of life, on how we look for life elsewhere in the universe. Due to its clear skies, by 2020, 60 percent of the biggest telescopes on Earth will be located in the Atacama, and while everyone else will be looking among the stars to answer the question, "Are we alone?" I will be looking down to the ground searching for this same answer in my own backyard. Thank you. (Applause)
En esta búsqueda, tratábamos de encontrar realmente el límite seco para la vida en la Tierra, un lugar tan seco que nada pudo sobrevivir en él. Pero incluso aquí, bien escondido bajo tierra, encontramos una cantidad de microorganismos diversos, lo que me sugirió que lugares similarmente secos, como Marte, pueden estar habitados. Incluso tenemos algunas evidencias preliminares de que estos microorganismos aún pueden estar activos en el estado desecado, como momias que caminan a nuestro alrededor, y que pueden estar usando la radiación UV como fuente de energía. Si se confirma, esto tendría gran impacto en nuestra definición de vida, sobre cómo buscamos la vida en otro lugar del universo. Debido a su cielo despejado, para el 2020 el 60 % de los mayores telescopios en la Tierra estará ubicado en Atacama, y mientras todos los demás mirarán entre las estrellas para responder a la pregunta: "¿Estamos solos?" yo estaré mirando hacia el suelo buscando esta misma respuesta en mi propio patio trasero. Gracias. (Aplausos)